Guide to the Louise Diamond papers, 1994-2010
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Louise Diamond papers
1994-2010
C0248
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
3.0 linear feet (5 boxes)
The Louise Diamond papers consist of documents on workshops, writings, consultations, and accompanying audio visual materials written by or involving Diamond.
Diamond, Louise, 1944-2015
Access Restrictions
File 3 of Box 3 is restricted. There are no access restrictions for the rest of the collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Louise Diamond in 2014.
Biographical Information
Louise Diamond was a founder and co-founder of several peace study policy groups, including Sunray Meditation Society in Lincoln, VT, the Institute for Multi-Track Diplomacy in Washington, D.C., The Peace Company in Bristol, VT, and Networks Inc. in Burlington, VT. As a citizen peacemaker, she traveled globally to teach peacebuilding and nonviolent conflict resolution - often in active war zones - as well as supported other peacemakers in their endeavors. Diamond wrote many articles on the subject of peace and conflict resolution, and the articles were published in a wide variety of journals, magazines, and books. She held several degrees, including a Ph.D. in Peace Studies from the Union Institute in Cincinnati, Ohio (1990). Diamond was a longtime resident of Vermont, USA, and passed away in May 2015.
Scope and Content
The Louise Diamond papers consist of documents on workshops, writings, consultations, and accompanying audio visual materials written by or involving Diamond. Subjects include Diamond's company, The Peace Company, and workshops surrounding the subject of international peacebuilding, diplomacy, and conflict resolution. These documents also pertain to peacebuilding in specific countries, such as Cyprus, Bosnia, and Kenya.
Arrangement
This collection was arranged in the original order it was received from the donor.
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives holds several other notable collections on conflict analysis and resolution including the Harold Saunders papers, the, and the.
Index Terms
Persons:
Diamond, Louise, 1944-2015.
Subjects:
Conflict management.
Contents List
  - Articles and Writing on "The Courage for Peace" by Diamond, 1999 - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Early Writings by Louise Diamond - Application to Ph. D. Program, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Whole Business Documents, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Publications - Conflict Transformation and Peacemakers, October 1993, January 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Writings - Peace and Diplomacy, 1998 - 1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Elders in Touch - Bristol Sale - Senior Herald Newspapers, January - July, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Peace Company Corporate Documents - Investor's Invitation, June 2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Peace Company Corporate Documents - Business Plan, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Beyond Win/Win: A Guide for Peacebuilders" - Publisher's Package - Never Completed, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Peace Company Corporate Documents - Shareholders' Report, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Peace Company Corporate Documents - Shareholders' Report, June 2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Peace Company Corporate Document - Investors' Invitation, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Foundations of Peacebuilding - Course Outline and Notes, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Staying Sane in a War Zone - Workshop Documents, November 1, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Peace Company Documents/Articles, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Peace Compan Corporate Documents - Confidential Private Placement Memorandum, June 16, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - How to Change the World: Intensive - Outline, Documents, and Articles, July 2008 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Psychology, Peacebuilding, and the Body Politic - Workshop Training Materials, October 23-25, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Olania Simulation Documents, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Peace and Conflict Workshops, 2000 - 2005 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Santa Fe Peace Conference Documents, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - World Bank Training Documents, circa 2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Peacebuilding Training Materials, circa 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Care Training Curriculum, circa 2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Care Academy Documents, 2003- 2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Heifer International and Diversity Documents, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tibet in Exile Peacebuilding Documents, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Kenya - Consultation Report - Conflict Resolution, March 29, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bosnian Youth Program - Snjezana Documents, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bosnia Peacebuilding Documents, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Care Sri Lanka Workshop Documents, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Cyprus Training and Consortium Documents, 1997 - 1999 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Cyprus Study Group Documents - Restricted, May 1999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Systems and Policy Documents, circa 2011 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Simple Rules of Systems Thinking for Peacebuilding Presentation Documents, circa 2008 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Systems and Policy Forum Documents, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Women in International Security Documents, circa 2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Diamond Peace Leadership Circle Documents, circa 2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Rivers of Hope Initiative Documents, April 15, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Cooperative Threat Reduction Documents, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Synopsis of Systems Salon Programs, 2010 - 2011 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Systems Writing Documents, 2001 - 2009 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Systems Writing Documents, 1997 - 2001 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Systems Writing Documents, 2007 - 2010 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Articles on Trauma Cycles, circa 1999 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Articles on Systems Changes, circa 2010 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - The Healing Power of Peace CD, circa 2007 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - In These Times CD, circa 2007 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Peace: The Next Frontier CD, circa 2007 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Peacebuilding in Everyday Life CD, circa 2007 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Humankind - NPR Peacebuilding Talk with Louise Diamond CD, circa 2007 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - In These Times CD, circa 2007 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - World Peace Conference Presentation - Jody Williams CD, May 2007 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - World Peace Conference Presentation - Aron Gandh CD, May 2007 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - World Peace Conference Presentation - Rigoberth Mencho Tom CD, May 2007 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - His Holiness the 14th Dalai Lama DVD, May 2007 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Shazam! Stories from a Life of Spirit-in-Action DVD, circa 2007 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Thumb Drive containing Digital Materials (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Peacebuilding in Every Day Life - A Home Study Program" Documents, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cyprus Conflict Management Program, July 4-10, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "The Whisper Tree" Documents, circa 2000 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "How to Change the World" Documents, circa 1995 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "How to Change the World" Documents - Part 2, circa 2007 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "How to Change the World" Documents - Part 3, circa 1999, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "How to Change the World" Documents - Part 4, circa 2008 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Forum on Systems Thinking For Complex Global Issues, November 10-11, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "AU Course" - Systems Approach to Peacebuilding Documents, February 13-15, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 9)